A Guide to the Edward Payson Roe Collection
University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, #7922-a
Edward Payson Roe Collection 1871-1888
University of Virginia. Library. Special Collections Dept. Alderman Library University of Virginia Charlottesville, Virginia 22903 USA
7922-a
20 items
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Deposit [ 17 Dec 1963 ] 14 Nov 1966
Item Listing
- Manucript
  - "Fruit and Nut Trees: An Arbor-Day-Plea", AMsS, 10 p.
    [Tipped into booklet.]
- Letters
  - Edward Payson Roe to Charles Mumford, 1871 May 13; ALS, 1 p.
    [Encloses [manuscript ?]; indicates his willingness to cut it if it is too long; invites him to visit; writes that he will soon send a check for $20.]
  - Edward Payson Roe to Charles W. [Squires], 1874 Oct 9; ALS, 1 p.
    [Sends autograph in response to request for [Squire's] collection of "Knights of the Quill."]
  - Edward Payson Roe to A. H. Holloway, 1877 Feb 27; ALS, 1 p.
    [Thanks him for "interesting volume."]
  - Edward Payson Roe to Frank S. Wood, 1879 Apr 22; ALS, 1 p.
    [Expresses thanks for being honored by Wood's Society.]
  - Edward Payson Roe to Editors, Youth's Companion, 1884 Oct 21; ALS, 8 p.
    [Outlines a story of a war refugee family based on
    Memoirs of the War of the Revolution in the Southern Dept. of the United States
    indicates his desire to produce what the editors want and to cooperate in every way; hopes for sufficient remuneration as he is financially pressed.]
  - Edward Payson Roe to [Samuel Sidney] McClure, 1884 Oct 22; ALS, 1 p.
    [Approves circular and hopes to hear from McClure about his sister's [ Mary Abigail Roe] story as well as his own.]
  - Edward Payson Roe to S[amuel] S[idney] McClure, 1885 May 9; ALS, 1 p.
    [Writes that, because of the volume of other work, he must know when the requested piece would be required and what he would receive for it before making a commitment.]
  - Edward Payson Roe to [Samuel Sidney] McClure, 1885 Aug 27; ALS, 2 p.
    [Writes that
    Current
    , which had been publishing a story of his, failed; fears he will suffer financial loss as a result; states that failure has impelled him to write "
    Significant Hummingbirds
    , " which he describes, to recoup losses; offers to sell it for $200.]
  - Edward Payson Roe to S[amuel] S[idney] McClure, 1885 Sep 7; ALS, 1 p.
    [Writes that, although he has had another offer for ["
    "], he has awaited McClure's response; sends the manuscript and points out its timeliness, because much criticism is being expressed of "wearing little birds."]
  - Edward Payson Roe to [Samuel Sidney] McClure, 1885 Sep 22; ALS, 1 p.
    [Excuses his delay in replying because he was on a mountain excursion with [Henry Mills] Alden; accepts the rejection of his story and will try again.]
  - Edward Payson Roe to [Samuel Sidney] McClure, 1885 Nov 11; ALS, 1 p.
    [Writes that he will meet McClure in December to discuss requests; states he is reluctant to take on new commitments because of promised work; hopes to begin war stories shortly; explains that he must write when the mood strikes rather than promise "a certain length and at a certain time"; writes he must complete work for
    Harper's [Monthly]
    . ]
  - Edward Payson Roe to S[amuel] S[idney] McClure, 1885 Dec 2; ALS, 2 p.
    [Explains the illness of his child prevented their planned meeting; requests a letter stating the type of work desired; states he will do his best but cannot meet demands as to length and completion date.]
  - Edward Payson Roe to [Samuel Sidney] McClure, 1885 Dec 10; ALS, 1 p.
    [States that he is writing a book which will provide more income that short stories; writes he will communicate with McClure when he has more time for stories.]
  - Edward Payson Roe to Perry, Mason & Co., 1886 Feb 3; ALS, 3 p.
    [Discusses a short story, which he has almost completed; writes he will submit it to [
    Youth's Companion
    ], his first attempt having been rejected; comments on a story which recently appeared in their publication which affected him deeply.]
  - Edward Payson Roe to Editor, New York Star, 1886 Feb 4; ALS, 3 p.
    [Discusses observance of the Sabbath and the role of Sunday newspapers; believes Sunday should be set apart from the rest of the week and publications should emphasize literature and articles leading to "higher thoughts... and better living" rather than business and crime.]
  - Edward Payson Roe to Perry, Mason & Co., 1886 Apr 24; ALS, 2 p.
    [Expresses understanding of an editor's right to choose his material and accepts the rejection of his story, which he has submitted elsewhere; writes that he is "mulish enough" to try again.]
  - Edward Payson Roe to S[amuel] S[idney] McClure, 1886 Nov 8; ALS, 2 p.
    [Writes that he has returned from Charleston with material for a story; states he will leave in 2 weeks for Santa Barbara, California with his family; expects the railroad companies and Santa Barbara to profit from his literary work; hopes for financial concessions; explains that, having "endorsed for a relative and lost everything," he is in financial difficulty.]
  - Edward Payson Roe to F. B. Wright, [Editor, the Graphic News ], 1887 Feb 9; ALS, 1 p.
    [Accepts, on behalf of his friend, whatever seems fair for the manuscript and photographs; believes the article will be an attractive feature in Wright's magazine.]
  - Edward Payson Roe to Editor, Lippincott's Magazine, 1888 Apr 9; ALS, 1 p.
    [Offers for publication a love story, "
    A Queen of Spades
    , " for which he asks $300 to be paid as soon as possible; reserves the right to publish in book form at a later date.]